<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="exp" docName="atommedia-00" ipr="none">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="AtomMedia">Atom Media Extensions</title>

    <author fullname="Martin Atkins" initials="M." surname="Atkins">
      <organization>Six Apart Ltd</organization>
    </author>

    <date />

    <abstract>
      <t>This document presents an extension to the Atom Syndication Format
      that defines how media objects such as photos and videos might be
      represented in Atom and allows additional metadata to be published about
      linked media representations.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This document presents an extension to <xref target="RFC4287">the
      Atom Syndication Format</xref> that defines how media objects such as
      photos and videos might be represented in Atom and allows additional
      metadata to be published about linked media representations.</t>

      <t>The capabilities described herein are an adaptation to Atom of some
      of the core capabilities of <xref target="MediaRSS"></xref>.</t>

      <t>This specification primarily considers the image, video and audio
      media types. The extensions described herein MAY be used with other
      media types in a way that is consistent with the definitions described
      in this specification, but this specification does not consider the
      processing expectations for such use.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Notational Conventions">
      <t>The XML Namespaces URI [W3C.REC-xml-names-19990114] for the XML
      elements and attributes described in this specification is: <spanx
      style="verb">http://purl.org/syndication/atommedia</spanx>.</t>

      <t>In this document, the namespace prefix "media:" is used for the above
      Namespace URI. The namespace prefix "atom:" is used for the namespace
      URI <spanx style="verb">http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom</spanx>. Note that
      the choices of namespace prefix are arbitrary and not semantically
      significant.</t>

      <t>This specification uses a shorthand form of terms from the XML
      Infoset [W3C.REC-xml-infoset-20040204]. The phrase "Information Item" is
      omitted when naming Element and Attribute Information Items. Therefore,
      when this specification uses the term "element," it is referring to an
      Element Information Item in Infoset terms. Likewise, when this
      specification uses the term "attribute," it is referring to an Attribute
      Information Item.</t>

      <t>This specification allows the use of IRIs [RFC3987]. Every URI
      [RFC3986] is also an IRI, so a URI may be used wherever an IRI is named.
      When an IRI that is not also a URI is given for dereferencing, it MUST
      be mapped to a URI using the steps in Section 3.1 of [RFC3987]. When an
      IRI is serving as an identifier, it MUST NOT be so mapped.</t>

      <t>Some sections of this specification are illustrated with a non-
      normative RELAX NG Compact schema [RELAXNG]. In those sections, this
      specification uses the atomCommonAttributes, atomMediaType, and atomURI
      patterns, defined in [RFC4287].</t>

      <t>However, the text of this specification provides the sole definition
      of conformance.</t>

      <t>This specification uses "the Atom specification" to refer to <xref
      target="RFC4287"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Media Objects as Atom Entries">
      <t>The Atom Syndication Format defines a set of elements which are
      designed primarily for use in describing weblog entries. When an Atom
      entry is used instead to represent a media object, such as a photo,
      video or audio recording, several additional items of information are
      useful, including links to a variety of representations of the media
      object as well as smaller "preview" representations that a user may view
      to decide whether to retrieve a representation of the full media
      object.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Link Relations">
      <t>This specification refines the existing "enclosure" and "alternate"
      link relations, and adds an additional "preview" link relation. These
      are described in the following sections.</t>

      <section title="The &quot;enclosure&quot; link relation">
        <t>The "enclosure" link relation is defined by section 4.2.7.2 of
        <xref target="RFC4287"></xref>. This section describes additional
        requirements for the use of this link relation in entries that
        represent media objects.</t>

        <t>When used in a media object entry, the enclosure link relation
        indicates that the link is to a representation of the media object.
        The <spanx style="verb">type</spanx> attribute indicates the media
        type of the representation.</t>

        <t>Links with this relationship SHOULD include any appropriate
        extension attributes from <xref target="attributes"></xref> as a hint
        to processors about which representations may be most appropriate for
        their capabilities or circumstances or those of the user.</t>

        <t>The <spanx style="verb">title</spanx> attribute MAY be used to
        provide a human-readable label to distinguish one representation from
        another. For example, <spanx style="verb">title="Full Size"</spanx>.
        Including media type information in the <spanx style="verb">title</spanx>
        attribute is however NOT RECOMMENDED, since this information can be
        derived from the <spanx style="verb">type</spanx> attribute if
        needed.</t>

        <t>As advised by the Atom specification, the <spanx style="verb">length</spanx>
        attribute SHOULD be used for link elements with this relation.</t>

        <t>Because this link relation is defined by the Atom specification,
        publishers should be aware that it may be processed by general Atom
        processors that do not support the media extensions described in this
        specification.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="The &quot;preview&quot; link relation">
        <t>The "preview" link relation indicates that the link is to a
        reduced-fidelity and/or reduced-content representation of the media
        object that is intended to allow the user to sample the content before
        retrieving a full representation. For example, if the media object is
        an image a thumbnail of the photograph can be linked using this
        relationship. If the media object is a video, the preview could be a
        thumbnail image of a representative frame from the video, or a clip
        showing a short segment of the full video. The <spanx style="verb">type</spanx>
        attribute indicates the media type of the representation.</t>

        <t>Resources linked with this relationship SHOULD be small in all
        appropriate senses of the word. In all cases they SHOULD have a lower
        filesize than the corresponding full representation. For preview
        representations with a visible manifestation, such as images and
        videos, the resource SHOULD have a small physical size in both
        dimensions such that the preview could readily be displayed on-screen
        with the previews from several other media items. For time-based
        media, the preview resource SHOULD have a short duration. No hard
        limits are placed on previews by this specification since it is
        anticipated that future technological advances such as larger or
        higher-resolution displays will lead to more more liberal definitions
        of "small".</t>

        <t>Links with this relationship SHOULD include any appropriate
        extension attributes from <xref target="attributes"></xref> as a hint
        to processors about which representations may be most appropriate for
        their capabilities or circumstances or those of the user.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="The &quot;alternate&quot; link relation">
        <t>When used in an Atom entry representing a media object, the
        "alternate" link relation is interpreted as a link to a document that
        itself contains the metadata about the media object and embeds or
        links to one or more representations of the media object.</t>

        <t>For example, if the <spanx style="verb">type</spanx> attribute
        contains <spanx style="verb">text/html</spanx>, the target of the link
        SHOULD be a HTML page that describes the media object, including
        metadata such as the title and description, and embeds and/or links to
        one or more representations of the object.</t>

        <t>If the <spanx style="verb">type</spanx> attribute contains a media
        type for embedded applets, such as <spanx style="verb">application/x-shockwave-flash</spanx>,
        the linked object SHOULD be an applet that can display or plays back
        the media object when executed. This applet MAY also make available
        through its user interface metadata such as the title and description
        for use when the applet is displayed alone without any other context.
        The <spanx style="verb">media:width</spanx> and <spanx style="verb">media:height</spanx>
        extension attributes described in <xref target="widthheight"></xref>
        SHOULD be included and SHOULD indicate the applet's native or ideal
        display size and aspect ratio.</t>

        <t>Because this link relation is defined by the Atom specification,
        publishers should be aware that it may be processed by general Atom
        processors that do not support the media extensions described in this
        specification.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="attributes" title="Link Extension Attributes">
      <t>The following extension attributes apply to the <spanx style="verb">atom:link</spanx>
      element. They provide a processing application with hints about the
      nature of the linked resource such that the application can choose an
      appropriate representation or representations from those available
      without retrieving all of the resources for examination. These extension
      attributes MUST NOT be assumed to provide completely accurate
      information about the linked resource. The non-authoritative nature of
      "external reference metadata", like the replies link attributes, is
      discussed in detail in Section 3.3 of <xref target="TAG12"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Implementors must be aware that although the Atom specification
      explicitly allows the link element to contain arbitrary extensions, the
      specification does not require that implementations support such
      extensions. In particular, these extension attributes may be lost if a
      feed is accessed through a feed re-publishing system that does not
      support these extensions.</t>

      <t>These extension attributes are intended to be used with links using
      the <spanx style="verb">enclosure</spanx> and <spanx style="verb">preview</spanx>
      link relations. They MAY be used with other link relations, but the
      processing expectations for such usage is not considered by this
      specification.</t>

      <section anchor="widthheight"
               title="The media:width and media:height Extension Attributes">
        <t>For media types that have an on-screen visible representation, in
        particular media types matching <spanx style="verb">image/*</spanx>
        and <spanx style="verb">video/*</spanx>, the <spanx style="verb">media:width</spanx>
        and <spanx style="verb">media:height</spanx> attributes specify the
        physical dimensions of the linked representation in whole media
        pixels.</t>

        <t>When used with arbitrarily scalable media such as vector graphics,
        these attributes specify an ideal or standard rendering size and
        aspect ratio. The same representation MAY be linked several times with
        different values of width and height.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="The media:duration Extension Attribute">
        <t>For time-based media types, in particular media types matching
        <spanx style="verb">video/*</spanx> and <spanx style="verb">audio/*</spanx>,
        the media:duration attribute specifies the length of time that the
        media object plays in whole seconds. If the exact duration is not a
        whole number of seconds, publishers MUST round the value to an integer
        in any way they deem appropriate.</t>

        <t>For links with the relation <spanx style="verb">preview</spanx>,
        this attribute (as well as the duration of the linked resource) SHOULD
        be less than or equal to the duration of the corresponding full
        representation.</t>

        <t>If a given entry contains several links with the <spanx
        style="verb">enclosure</spanx> relation that have a media:duration
        attribute, the duration of all of the resources linked in this way
        SHOULD have the same or at least a similar duration since they are
        alternative representations of the same content.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="The media:description Extension Element">
      <t>The <spanx style="verb">media:description</spanx> extension element
      is used as a child of <spanx style="verb">atom:entry</spanx> and
      contains a human-readable description, usually provided by the author of
      the media object, of the content of the media object. It is distinct
      from the <spanx style="verb">atom:content</spanx> element because the
      latter contains more general content suitable for displaying this object
      in a general Atom processor that does not support the media extensions
      described in this specification.</t>

      <t>The content model and processing requirements of this element are the
      same as for atom:content, including attributes, as described in section
      4.1.3 of the Atom specification.</t>

      <t>An <spanx style="verb">atom:entry</spanx> element MUST NOT contain
      more than one <spanx style="verb">media:description</spanx> element.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Publishing Conventions For Specific Media Types">
      <t>This section defines specific applications of the above mechanisms
      for publishing the three different media types considered by this
      specification.</t>

      <section title="Photos and Other Images">
        <t>When publishing images, all representations are usually in media
        types that match <spanx style="verb">image/*</spanx>. While publishers
        are free to provide representations in any number of formats, a
        representation of type <spanx style="verb">image/jpeg</spanx>, <spanx
        style="verb">image/png</spanx> or <spanx style="verb">image/gif</spanx>
        SHOULD be provided. Processors SHOULD support at least these three
        media types for both images and image previews.</t>

        <t>Although both the "enclosure" and "preview" link relations can link
        to representations of any size, publishers SHOULD use "enclosure" only
        for representations that are of a size suitable for viewing alone
        on-screen. Conversely, publishers SHOULD use "preview" only for
        representations that are of a size suitable for displaying alongside
        other image previews, such that the user may choose one image to view
        in full.</t>

        <t>At least one "enclosure" link SHOULD be provided. Including at
        least one "preview" link is RECOMMENDED.</t>

        <t>If the author has provided a title or short caption for the image,
        it SHOULD be included in the <spanx style="verb">atom:title</spanx>
        element. In the absense of such a title, publishers MAY substitute a
        filename or other identifier that might allow a human to recognise the
        image.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Video">
        <t>When publishing video, representations with various container
        formats and codecs are generally published for maximum compatibility.
        Publishers may choose also to provide audio-only versions of the
        content. Finally, at least one image is often provided showing a
        representative frame from the video.</t>

        <t>When linking to the actual video content <spanx style="verb">rel="enclosure"</spanx>
        MUST be used with a suitable media type. Including such a link is
        RECOMMENDED. Implementers should be aware that for video content the
        base media type often refers only to the container format and does not
        describe the audio or video codecs used. Identifying the codecs used
        within particular container formats is the responsibility of each
        container's media type; it is out of scope for this specification.
        Publishers SHOULD include the <spanx style="verb">media:duration</spanx>
        extension attribute on each enclosure link, but the duration SHOULD be
        the same or similar for all such links since they represent the same
        content. Processors MAY display the duration from any included
        enclosure link as a single display duration for all
        representations.</t>

        <t>Publishers SHOULD provide at least one thumbnail image of type
        <spanx style="verb">image/jpeg</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">image/png</spanx>
        or <spanx style="verb">image/gif</spanx> that is taken from a
        representative frame of the video, and link to this image with <spanx
        style="verb">rel="preview"</spanx>.</t>

        <t>If an audio-only representation of the content is provided, and the
        audio is considered to be a usable full representation of the content,
        it MUST be included with <spanx style="verb">rel="enclosure"</spanx>
        and a suitable media type. Publishers SHOULD include the <spanx
        style="verb">media:duration</spanx> extension attribute on such links
        and the duration SHOULD be the same or similar to the corresponding
        video representation. If the audio is provided only as a preview of
        the resource, <spanx style="verb">rel="preview"</spanx> MUST be
        used.</t>

        <t>If an applet such as a Flash player is available to play back the
        video, it SHOULD be linked with <spanx style="verb">rel="alternate"</spanx>
        and an appropriate media type. For a Flash-based player the
        appropriate media type is <spanx style="verb">application/x-shockwave-flash</spanx>,
        and <spanx style="verb">href</spanx> should contain a URL that could
        be used in the <spanx style="verb">src</spanx> attribute of the HTML
        <spanx style="verb">embed</spanx> element with this type. It is
        acknowledged that in many cases more than just a URL is required to
        successfully embed a movie player applet, but a mechanism for
        obtaining the additional information is out of scope for this
        specification. Publishers MAY include more complete embedding code as
        part of the value of <spanx style="verb">atom:content</spanx>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Audio">
        <t>When linking to the actual audio content <spanx style="verb">rel="enclosure"</spanx>
        MUST be used with a suitable media type. Publishers SHOULD include the
        <spanx style="verb">media:duration</spanx> extension attribute on each
        enclosure link, but the duration SHOULD be the same or similar for all
        such links since they represent the same content. Processors MAY
        display the duration from any included enclosure link as a single
        display duration for all representations.</t>

        <t>If an applet such as a Flash player is available to play back the
        audio, it SHOULD be linked with <spanx style="verb">rel="alternate"</spanx>
        and an appropriate media type. For a Flash-based player the
        appropriate media type is <spanx style="verb">application/x-shockwave-flash</spanx>,
        and <spanx style="verb">href</spanx> should contain a URL that could
        be used in the <spanx style="verb">src</spanx> attribute of the HTML
        <spanx style="verb">embed</spanx> element with this type.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Conventions for All Media Types">
        <t>This section describes some conventions that are applicable to all
        media types, in many cases relating to handling of media entries by
        general Atom processors that do not support media extensions.</t>

        <t>If the author has provided a textual description for the image, it
        SHOULD be included in the <spanx style="verb">media:description</spanx>
        extension element. Publishers SHOULD include an <spanx style="verb">atom:content</spanx>
        element in each media object entry containing HTML that, when
        displayed to a user, communicates all information necessary to
        interact with the resource in conjunction with the values of other
        elements defined by the Atom specification. This content will be used
        by Atom processors that do not support media extensions.</t>

        <t>Processors that <spanx>do</spanx> support media extensions MAY use
        the information provided by the extension attributes and elements
        defined in this specification in place of the value of <spanx
        style="verb">atom:content</spanx>. This is because <spanx
        style="verb">atom:content</spanx> will in most cases contain
        information that duplicates that provided by the media extension
        constructs. Processors MAY offer to users a way to access the fallback
        content in preference to the information provided by the media
        extension constructs.</t>

        <t>Publishers SHOULD include in each media object entry an <spanx
        style="verb">atom:link</spanx> element with the relation "alternate"
        and the media type <spanx style="verb">text/html</spanx> whose target
        is an HTML page that represents the media object, includes metadata
        such as the title and description and embeds and/or links to one or
        more representations of the media object for the benefit of a human
        user.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>As this specification defines an extension to the Atom Syndication
      Format, it is subject to the same security considerations defined in
      <xref target="RFC4287"></xref>.</t>

      <t>[TODO: Write some more here.]</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>[TODO: Write up a registration entry for the new "preview" link
      relation.]</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC4287">
        <front>
          <title>The Atom Syndication Format</title>

          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title>RFC 2119</title>

          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3987">
        <front>
          <title>Internationalized Resource Identifiers (IRIs)</title>

          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MediaRSS">
        <front>
          <title>MediaRSS</title>

          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TAG12">
        <front>
          <title>TAG Finding 12: Authoritative Metadata</title>

          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>...</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Examples">
      <t>This appendix is non-normative.</t>

      <t>The examples in this section are given as standalone entries without
      a containing feed. It should be assumed that in each of these examples
      the following XML namespace declarations are in scope: <spanx
      style="verb">xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://example.com/to-be-confirmed"</spanx>.</t>

      <section title="Photo Entry">
        <figure>
          <preamble>The following example shows an Atom entry representing a
          photo</preamble>

          <artwork><![CDATA[<entry>
    <title>My Cats</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
          href="http://photopanic.example.com/cats.html"/>
    <id>tag:photopanic.example.com,2008:cats</id>
    <published>2008-12-13T23:09:02Z</published>
    <updated>2008-12-13T23:09:02Z</updated>
    <link rel="enclosure" type="image/jpeg"
          href="http://photopanic.example.com/cats_m.jpg"
          media:width="640" media:height="480"
          title="Medium-size" length="53433" />
    <link rel="enclosure" type="image/jpeg"
          href="http://photopanic.example.com/cats_f.jpg"
          media:width="1280" media:height="1024"
          title="Full-size" length="4353433" />
    <link rel="preview" type="image/jpeg"
          href="http://photopanic.example.com/cats_t.jpg"
          media:width="100" media:height="100"
          length="2048" />
    <media:description>My cats: Tom, Henrietta and Billy.</media:description>          

    <content type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;
            &lt;a
                href=&quot;http://photopanic.example.com/cats.html&quot;
                title=&quot;My Cats&quot;&gt;
                &lt;img
                    src=&quot;http://photopanic.example.com/cats_m.jpg&quot;
                    width=&quot;640&quot;
                    height=&quot;480&quot;
                /&gt;
            &lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/p&gt;
    </content>
</entry>]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Video Entry">
        <figure>
          <preamble>The following example shows an Atom entry representing a
          video.</preamble>

          <artwork><![CDATA[<entry>
    <title>Duct Tape</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
          href="http://ubertube.example.com/ducttape.html"/>
    <id>tag:ubertube.example.com,2005:ducttape</id>
    <published>2008-12-13T23:09:02Z</published>
    <updated>2008-12-13T23:09:02Z</updated>
    <link rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"
          href="http://ubertube.example.com/ducttape.mp4"
          media:width="640" media:height="480"
          length="3635674756" media:duration="170" />
    <link rel="enclosure" type="video/x-flv"
          href="http://ubertube.example.com/ducttape.flv"
          media:width="640" media:height="480"
          length="153463454" media:duration="170" />
    <link rel="preview" type="image/jpeg"
          href="http://ubertube.example.com/ducttape_t.jpg"
          media:width="100" media:height="100"
          length="2032" />
    <link rel="alternate" type="application/x-shockwave-flash"
          href="http://ubertube.example.com/ducttape_e.swf"
          media:width="640" media:height="480" />
    <media:description>
        Talking with Duct Tape over my mouth.
    </media:description>          

    <content type="html">
        &lt;embed
          src="http://ubertube.example.com/ducttape_e.swf"
          type="application/x-shockwave-flash"
          width="640" height="480"&gt;
    </content>
</entry>]]></artwork>

          <postamble>The video itself is provided in two different formats. A
          small preview image is provided. An applet to play back the video is
          also provided and embedded in the HTML included in the content
          element.</postamble>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
